Guide to the Sallie Bingham Papers, 1900-2023 and undated RL.00112
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Sallie Bingham papers
1900-2023 and undated
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Bingham, Sallie
RL.00112
93.75 Linear Feet
Feminist and author. The Sallie Bingham Papers provide rich documentation of the personal life, literary development, and philanthropic activities of Sallie Bingham, feminist and writer. The papers, dated 1900-2011, with the bulk of the materials dating from the 1940s to 2011, are comprised of correspondence, speeches, writings, subject files, personal papers, diaries and notebooks, legal and financial papers, audiovisual recordings, and photographic media. Included also are some records of The Kentucky Foundation for Women, a philanthropic organization founded by Bingham; The American Voice, a literary journal founded by Bingham and published under the auspices of The Kentucky Foundation for Women; and Santa Fe Stages, a regional theater founded by Bingham. Arranged into the following series: Audiovisual Materials, Correspondence, Diaries and Notebooks, Kentucky Foundation for Women, Legal and Financial, Miscellaneous, Photographs, Poetry, Santa Fe Stages, Speeches, Subject Files, Writings, and Oversize Material, with the Writings, Diaries and Notebooks, and Correspondence Series composing the bulk of the collection. Multiple additions have been added since the collection was processed; these are represented at the end of this finding aid.
Access Restrictions
Written permission from the donor, Sallie Bingham, is necessary before accessing the following: diaries, notebooks, correspondence, photographs, legal and financial papers, and files associated with the following: Kentucky Foundation for Women, The American Voice, and Santa Fe Stages. Not covered by this restriction: writings, speeches, clippings, subject files, audiovisual materials.
Provenance
The papers of Sallie Bingham, feminist, writer, and patron of the arts, were donated to the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library from 1988 to 2023.
Biographical Note
1937, January 22 Born Sarah Montague Bingham, Glenview, Ky.; spent childhood there.
1958 Mademoiselle guest editorship in fiction Married Whitney Ellsworth and lived in New York BA, Radcliffe College
1960 Published After Such Knowledge (novel)
1960, June 7 Son Barry Ellsworth born
1965 Married Michael Iovenko
1967, June 14 Son Christopher Iovenko born
1968 Published The Touching Hand (novella and short stories)
1970, March 3 Son William Iovenko born
1972 Publication of The Way It Is Now (short stories)
1977 Returned to Louisville, Kentucky
1980, March Produced Milk of Paradise (play)
1982-1985 Book editor, The Louisville Courier-Journal
1983, January Produced The Wall Between (play)
1983 Married Tim Peters
1983, November Produced Couvade (play)
1983-1986 Director, National Book Critics Circle
1984-1985 Produced Paducah (play)
1984-1988 Director, Spalding University
1985 Founder and publisher of The American Voice (literary journal) Founded The Kentucky Foundation for Women, Inc.
1985-1988 Director, Maryhurst Home for Girls
1986, January Sale of Bingham Enterprises
1986 Produced In the Presence (play)
1988 Produced Hopscotch (play)
1989, January Published Passion and Prejudice (memoir)
1989 Father Barry Bingham, Sr. dies Produced The Awakening (play)
1991 Moved to Santa Fe, New Mexico
1992 Published Small Victories (novel)
1993 Publication of Upstate: A Novel
1994 Founded Santa Fe Stages Published Matron of Honor (novel) Resigned from The Kentucky Foundation for Women, Inc.
1995 Mother, Mary Bingham, dies
1996 Published Straight Man (novel)
2002 Publication of Transgressions: Stories
2005 Publication of Cory's Feast (novel)
2006 Published The Hub of Miracle (poems) Published Nick of Time (novel)
2008 Publication by Sarabande Books of Red Car (short stories)
2011 Publication by Sarabande Books of Mending: New and Selected Stories
Collection Overview
The Sallie Bingham Papers provide rich documentation of the personal life, literary development, and philanthropic activities of Sallie Bingham, feminist and writer. The papers, dated 1900-2022, with the bulk of the materials dating from the 1940s to 2022, are comprised of correspondence, speeches, writings, subject files, personal papers, diaries and notebooks, legal and financial papers, audiovisual recordings, and photographic media. Included also are some records of The Kentucky Foundation for Women, a philanthropic organization founded by Bingham; The American Voice, a literary journal founded by Bingham and published under the auspices of The Kentucky Foundation for Women; and Santa Fe Stages, a regional theater founded by Bingham. Arranged into the following series: Audiovisual Materials, Correspondence, Diaries and Notebooks, Kentucky Foundation for Women, Legal and Financial, Miscellaneous, Photographs, Poetry, Santa Fe Stages, Speeches, Subject Files, Writings, and Oversize Material, with the Writings, Diaries and Notebooks, and Correspondence Series composing the bulk of the collection.
The Writings Series is central to the collection, and is correspondingly substantial, comprising over half of the papers. It includes drafts, research, correspondence and publicity related to such novels as Small Victories, Upstate, Matron of Honor, and Straight Man, her memoir Passion and Prejudice, the writing and production of the plays The Awakening and The Death of Henry Flagler as well as poetry and many short, personal essays. The Poetry Series consists of individual poems, while compendiums of poetry are in the Writings Series. Many of Bingham's writings (including poems, novels, short stories, plays and essays) exist as electronic files and are available to researchers. These files are listed in the Poetry and the Writings Series. The Diaries and Notebooks Series contains material spanning her entire life -- from her adolescence in Louisville, Kentucky in the 1940s to her experiences living in Santa Fe, New Mexico, and contain many ideas for writings and references to the process of writing. The Correspondence Series also spans the same period of time, and contains family correspondence spanning many decades, as well as literary and personal correspondence between Bingham and such well-known authors, activists and artists as Judy Chicago and Gloria Steinem. The smaller Speeches Series houses writings by Bingham for public engagements, and in addition to contributing to a portrait of Bingham as a writer, documents her explication of feminist issues relating to women in the corporate world, in publishing, and women in history.
Bingham, born into a prominent Louisville, KY, family that owned The Louisville Courier-Journal, worked for the newspaper as book page editor, 1982-1985. She also took an active seat on the board of the Bingham Enterprises, which was responsible for The Courier-Journal and other media corporations in the Louisville area. Bingham's desire to sell her shares in the stock in the newspaper resulted in the sale of The Courier-Journal in 1986. The Bingham family and the break-up of the Bingham Enterprises were the subject of at least four books (The Binghams of Louisville, House of Dreams, The Patriarch, and Bingham's Passion and Prejudice) and much media attention. Materials concerning this aspect of Bingham's life can be found in the Legal and Financial Papers Series and Subject Files Series. Audiovisual materials in the Audiotapes and Videotapes Series document aspects of Bingham's career and life through interviews and other events.
NOTE: This collection also contains numerous additions that have not been processed. For descriptions of later additions, please see below or consult the library's online catalog.
Related Material
Related research materials at Duke include the Mary Ellen Miller Papers, which contain primarily personal and professional correspondence from Sallie Bingham to Miller, as well as the Kentucky Foundation for Women Records, an organization founded by Sallie Bingham.
Papers of Sallie Bingham's father, George Barry Bingham, are housed in The Filson Historical Society in Louisville, Ky. Papers of her grandfather, Robert Worth Bingham, are also housed at The Filson Historical Society and at the Library of Congress.
Mary Ellen Miller Papers, 1983-2001
Duke University. David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Kentucky Foundation for Women Records, 1985-1999 and undated
Duke University. David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
George Barry Bingham Papers, 1861-1989
The Filson Historical Society, Louisville, Ky.
Robert Worth Bingham Papers, 1876-1982
The Filson Historical Society, Louisville, Ky.
Robert Worth Bingham Papers, 1879-1974
Library of Congress
Robert Worth Bingham Papers, 1879-1974
Library of Congress
Robert Worth Bingham Papers, 1879-1974
Library of Congress
Wallace Literary Agency
Harry Ransom Center
Alfred A. Knopf
Harry Ransom Center
Theater -- United States -- History -- 20th century; American drama -- 20th century; Benefactors -- United States; Poetry; Feminism and literature -- United States; Feminism -- United States; American literature -- 20th century -- Periodicals; American literature -- Women authors; Embroidery (visual works); Holographs; Diaries; Jefferson County (Ky.); Color photographs; Black-and-white photographs; Videocassettes; Audiocassettes; Scrapbooks; Contact sheets; Roll negatives; Louisville (Ky.) -- History; Women authors, American -- 20th century; Women authors, American -- 20th century -- Correspondence; Authors and publishers; Machine-readable records; United States -- Newspapers; Santa Fe (N.M.) -- History; Santa Fe County (N.M.) -- History; Santa Fe Stages; Chicago, Judy, 1939-; Kentucky Foundation for Women; Bingham, Sallie; Center for Women's History and Culture; Bingham family; Bingham, Robert; Bingham, Mary Caperton, 1904-; Bingham, Sallie. Transgressions; Bingham, Sallie. Straight man; Bingham, Sallie. Upstate; Bingham, Sallie. Matron of honor; Bingham, Sallie. Manuscripts; Bingham, Sallie. Small victories; Bingham, Sallie. Passion and prejudice
- The American Voice Series, 1985-1998 (RESTRICTED)
  Scope and Contents note
  Contains various materials related to the publication of the literary journal, The American Voice (TAV). TAV was founded by Bingham and is published under the auspices of The Kentucky Foundation for Women. Arranged alphabetically.
  - The American Voice (Box 1)
    - No. 17, Winter, 1989 (Box 1)
    - No. 37, 1995 (Box 1)
    - No. 12, Fall, 1998 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence (Box 1)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 1)
  - Publicity (Box 1)
  - Submissions (Box 1)
- Audiotapes and Videotapes Series, 1980-1989
  Audio and video recordings of several of Bingham's plays and readings, and interviews on television and radio shows.
  Conditions Governing Access note
  [Original audiovisual materials are closed to use. Technical Services staff must arrange to have use copies made before contents can be accessed. Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use these materials.]
  - Audiotapes and Videotapes (Box 1)
- Correspondence Series, 1910-1998 (bulk 1940s-1998) (RESTRICTED)
  Contains the personal and professional correspondence of Sallie Bingham from the 1940s to 1998. It includes letters as a child and a schoolgirl to her nurse, letters to and from friends documenting her development as a writer and the details of her personal life, and later professional correspondence with writers, publishers, producers, and organizations. The correspondence for the years 1910-1950s is a mixture of letters to and from various family members such as Barry Bingham, Sr., Mary Bingham, Henrietta Bingham, and Robert "Judge" Bingham. Later correspondence is a mixture of literary and personal correspondence between Bingham and her colleagues and friends. Arranged chronologically by year.
  - 1910-1989 (20 folders) (Box 1)
  - 1989-1992 (23 folders) (Box 2)
  - 1993-1998 (14 folders) (Box 3)
- Diaries and Notebooks Series, 1945-1990s (RESTRICTED)
  Bingham's diaries document her daily activities, reflections on life, and contain some seed ideas for stories. Her notebooks function as workbooks for her writings and include poems, ideas for stories, outlines for plays, and character sketches - all in various stages of development. Arranged by format (diary or notebook) and then chronologically.
  - Diaries:
    - 1949-1950 (2 folders) (Box 1)
    - 1950-1963 (19 folders) (Box 2)
    - 1964-1978 (26 folders) (Box 3)
    - 1979-1993 (36 folders) (Box 4)
    - 1993-1996 and undated (24 folders) (Box 5)
  - Notebooks:
    - 1945-1996 and undated (27 folders) (Box 1)
- The Kentucky Foundation for Women Series, 1986-1998 (RESTRICTED)
  The Kentucky Foundation for Women is a philanthropic organization founded by Bingham, which seeks to support women in the arts in Kentucky. Thus, the Foundation gives out a number of grants for living expenses each year to Kentucky women artists in order to allow them time to focus on creative projects. The Foundation also publishes the literary journal The American Voice. This series contains miscellaneous administrative files regarding grant proposal guidelines, office procedures, and finances of The Kentucky Foundation for Women. Related material found in the Kentucky Foundation for Women Records, a separate collection housed in the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library. Arranged alphabetically.
  - Anne Maiken, 1986 (Box 1)
  - Annual report, 1988 (Box 1)
  - Board of Directors minutes, 1987-1998 (Box 1)
  - Bylaws (Box 1)
  - Correspondence, 1987-1998 (Box 1)
  - Employment policies (Box 1)
  - Executive director search, 1998 (Box 1)
  - Financial advisors, 1986 (Box 1)
  - Financial statements, 1986, 1988-1989 (Box 1)
  - Foundation material for speeches, 1985-1986 and undated (Box 1)
  - Foundation reorganization, 1986 (Box 1)
  - Fund for Women, Inc.: financial, 1986 (Box 1)
  - Funding proposals, 1987 and undated, -1988 (2 folders) (Box 1)
  - Grant application forms, undated (Box 1)
  - Grants, 1986, 1990, 1997-1998 (Box 1)
  - Hopscotch House (Box 1)
  - Information for Foundation position papers, undated (Box 1)
  - Institute for Creative Learning, 1986 (Box 1)
  - Maxine (internal planning document), undated (Box 1)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 1)
  - Newsletters, 1987-1989 (Box 1)
  - Notebook, 1986, 1988 (2 folders) (Box 1)
  - Position papers and application form, undated (Box 1)
  - Resignation letters:
    - Ann Stewart Anderson, 1997 (Box 1)
    - Sallie Bingham, 1994 (Box 1)
  - Spending policy, 1998 (Box 1)
  - Wolf Pen Writers Colony (Box 1)
- Legal and Financial Papers Series, 1930s-1998 (RESTRICTED)
  Contains Bingham's correspondence and notes about family members and management at The Louisville Courier-Journal, minutes from board meetings, and memorandums concerning the running of The C-J for the period leading up to the sale of Bingham Enterprises. Also included are legal papers pertaining to books written about the sale of Bingham Enterprises, legal and financial papers concerning Bingham's divorce from Tim Peters, as well as miscellaneous files relating to Sallie Bingham's property and finances in the 1980s and 1990s. Arranged alphabetically.
  - Askew-Petersen Stone Works (Box 1)
  - Bingham Enterprises:
    - Board memorandum, 1982 (Box 1)
    - Conversation with management and directors, 1983-1984 (Box 1)
    - Correspondence and notes on meetings with family, 1980-1984 (Box 1)
    - Directors and Stockholders meetings, 1984-1985 (4 folders) (Box 1)
    - Directors meetings, 1984-1985 (2 folders) (Box 1)
    - The Louisville Courier-Journal & Times Merger, 1985 (Box 1)
  - Dean Robertson (Box 1)
  - Donations to the Mary C. Bingham Memorial Fund, 1995 (Box 1)
  - Employment as Book Page Editor at The Louisville Courier-Journal, 1982-1985 (Box 1)
  - Estate papers and wills ( Sallie Bingham), 1989-1991 (Box 1)
  - Exhibits to Memorandum on The Binghams of Louisville (3 vols.) (Box 1)
  - Farm upkeep (Box 1)
  - Financial statements, 1986-1989 (Box 1)
  - Henrietta Bingham, 1930s-1940s (Box 1)
  - Itemized categories, 1997 (Box 1)
  - Libel law and cases, 1987-1988 (Box 1)
  - List of possessions, apartment renovations, etc., 1964 (Box 1)
  - Model contract (Author's Guild), 1972 (Box 1)
  - 1987 inheritance (Box 1)
  - Peters and Bingham Divorce:
    - Car insurance policies (Box 1)
    - The Cloisters (Box 1)
    - Correspondence (Box 1)
    - Decree of dissolution (Box 1)
    - Divorce preparation (Box 1)
    - Exhibits (Box 1)
    - Financial statements (Box 1)
    - Gentry vs. Gentry (Box 1)
    - Incidents and inventory of relationship (Box 2)
    - Judge Rebecca Westerfield (Box 2)
    - The Kentucky Foundation for Women (Box 2)
    - Kevin Nance re: property settlement (Box 2)
    - Key West house (Box 2)
    - Kirsten Martin statement (Box 2)
    - Miscellaneous Correspondence (Box 2)
    - Pre-nuptial agreement (Box 2)
    - Property laws: women and disqualified persons: legal definition (Box 2)
    - Release of Bingham diaries (Box 2)
    - Sally Peters statement (Box 2)
    - Surveillance of Tim Peters (Box 2)
    - Tim Peters' attorney fees (Box 2)
    - Tim Peters' claims for maintenance (Box 2)
    - Tim Peters' depositions (Box 2)
    - Trial brief and reply brief (Box 2)
    - Witness lists (Box 2)
  - Private gifts, undated (Box 2)
  - Sale of The Louisville Courier-Journal:
    - Confidentiality agreement, 1986 (Box 2)
    - Consensus letter, 1986 (Box 2)
    - Newspaper clippings, 1984-1991 (4 folders) (Box 2)
    - Stocks owned by S. Bingham, 1983-1985 (2 folders) (Box 2)
  - Spousal gifting, 1984 (Box 2)
  - Standard Gravure lawsuit (sex discrimination), 1987 (Box 2)
  - Studio, 1988 (Box 2)
  - Suppression of The Binghams of Louisville: newspaper clippings (1 folder) (Box 2)
  - 1099 form, 1995, 1997 (Box 2)
  - Trust Fund for Timothy Peters, Doug Peters, Elizabeth Bingham (Box 2)
  - Will ( Barry Bingham), 1988 (Box 2)
  - Will ( Mary Bingham), 1994 (Box 2)
- Miscellaneous Series, 1949-1958 and undated (RESTRICTED)
  Various unrelated items such as Bingham's wedding register, brother Jonathan's theater record book, personal correspondence and other items related to deaths in the family, and ephemeral items. Arranged alphabetically.
  - Miscellaneous (Box 1)
  - Theater Record, 1949 (Box 1)
  - Wedding Gift Book, 1958 (Box 1)
  - Wedding Register, 1958 (Box 1)
  - Miscellaneous Subject files (Box 2)
    - Barry Bingham Sr.'s death, 1988 (Box 2)
    - Agents (Bill Goodman), 1988-1993
      - Bill Goodman, 1994-1995 (Box 2)
      - Gloria Loomis, 1990-1994 (Box 2)
      - Miscellaneous, 1968-1997 (Box 2)
    - Suppression of The Binghams of Louisville: Correspondence, 1985-1988 (Box 2)
    - Mary Bingham's death, 1995:
      - Correspondence (Box 2)
      - Photos, newspaper clippings (Box 2)
      - Resolutions in honor of Mary Bingham (Box 2)
    - Calendars
      - 1987 (Box 2)
      - 1988-1989 (Box 2)
      - 1989 (Box 2)
- Photographs Series, circa 1900-1998 (RESTRICTED)
  Comprised chiefly of photographs (and some negatives) of family and friends. It includes early family photos circa 1900-1950s used in Passion and Prejudice, as well as snapshots, 1950s-1989, of Sallie Bingham's children, friends and relatives, attendance at various meetings or events, and some publicity photos. Photographs of actual play productions are filed with the individual plays in the Writings series. Arranged alphabetically.
  - Bingham School (Mebane, N.C.) and Bingham Grave (N.C.), 1980s (Box 1)
  - Miscellaneous, 1980s-1990s (Box 1)
  - Passion and Prejudice (photographs for book), 1900-1980: bulk 1900-1950 (Box 1)
  - Sallie Bingham family, 1900-1970s: bulk 1940s-1950s (2 folders) (Box 1)
  - Sallie Bingham, ca. 1960-1990s (2 folders) (Box 1)
- Poetry Series, 1977-1997
  Consists of two subseries: Paper Format and Electronic Format. The contents of the two subseries often overlap.
  - Paper Format Poetry Subseries, 1977-1997 and undated
    Consists of miscellaneous poems grouped into files and arranged chronologically by year. Please note that collections of poetry by Bingham are interfiled in the Writings Series. They are designated as such in the container list for that series so patrons can more easily locate them.
    - 1977 (Box 1)
    - 1980-1997 (Box 1)
    - 1987 (Box 1)
    - July, October 1989 (Box 1)
    - 1989 ("Not for Collection") (Box 1)
    - Fall, 1991 (Box 1)
    - Poems sent to Chelsea, 12/1991 (Box 1)
    - Winter, 1991/1992 (Box 1)
    - Poems sent to Sarah Gorham, 1993-1995 (Box 1)
    - Poems sent to Sarah Gorham, October 1995 (Box 1)
    - 1995 (Box 1)
    - 1995-1996 (Box 1)
    - Poems sent to Sarah Gorham, 1996 (Box 1)
    - 1996-1997 (Box 1)
    - "Poems from the Collection" November 1997 (Box 1)
    - Journal of Poems, 2004 (Box 1)
  - Electronic Format Poetry Subseries, 1994-1997 and undated
    Arranged by disk numbers, which were assigned only to reflect the original order in which they were received. The list below is arranged alphabetically by title to facilitate intellectual access. An individual poem's title is in quotation marks, followed by the file name, the year in which the electronic file was last modified, and the file's disk (subdirectory) name. A number of these poems exist in more than one iteration; they may have multiple file names and/or exist in multiple subdirectories. Note that many of the following poems possess multiple files that may have been created or edited in different years.
    The contents of each disk was migrated to the Specoll server. Consequently, the text of the poems is available only in correspondingly numbered electronic subdirectories. Consult a reference archivist for access to the electronic files.
    - Advent, Advent.poe, 1995, on Disk008 (Box 1)
    - Advice, Advice.poe, 1995, on Disk008 (Box 1)
    - Angel, Angel.poe, 1996 (on Disk007) and 1997 (on Disk008) (Box 1)
    - Apache, Apache.poe, 1997, on Disk008 (Box 1)
    - The Artist's Mate, Mate.poe, 1995, on Disk008 (Box 1)
    - As in the Moment, As.poe, 1997, on Disk008 (Box 1)
    - At the Dominicans, Desert.poe, 1996, on Disk003 (Box 1)
    - Avalanche Avalanch, 1997, on Disk003 (Box 1)
    - The Birds' Christmas, Birds.poe, 1997, on Disk003 (Box 1)
    - Birthday at the Beach, Birthday.poe, 1994, on Disk008 (Box 1)
    - Boccanera: Anatomia Del Corpo Umano, Staff.poe, 1995, on Disk008 (Box 1)
    - Boxcar, Boxcar.poe, 1996, on Disk008 (Box 1)
    - Button Box, Buttons.poe, 1997, on Disk003 (Box 1)
    - By the Fall, Fall.poe, 1996, on Disk007 and Disk008 (Box 1)
    - By the Lake, Lake.poe, 1995, on Disk007 and Disk008 (Box 1)
    - Chapel Stool, Stool, 1997, on Disk003 (Box 1)
    - Chocolate Pot, Chocolat, 1995 (on Disk007) and 1997 (on Disk008) (Box 1)
    - Christmas Day: Los Liandros, Los.poe, 1997, on Disk003 (Box 1)
    - Convention, Conventi.poe, 1994, on Disk008 (Box 1)
    - Cottonwood, Cottonwoo.poe, 1997, on Disk003 (Box 1)
    - Coyotes, Coyotes.poe, 1997, on Disk003 (Box 1)
    - Cupid and Psyche, Cupid.poe, 1995, on Disk008 (Box 1)
    - The Day Christ Died, Saturday.poe, 1996, on Disk010 (Box 1)
    - Deer Dance, Deer.poe, 1996, on Disk008 (Box 1)
    - Dionysus' Mother, Diony.poe, 1997, on Disk003 (Box 1)
    - Dressing Down, Dragon.poe, 1995, on Disk008 (Box 1)
    - Dr. Science, Dr.sci, 1996, on Disk003 (Box 1)
    - Drunk Indian, Drunk.poe, 1997, on Disk008 (Box 1)
    - The Dug Grave, Grave.poe, 1997, on Disk003 (Box 1)
    - Easter Vigil, Easter.poe, 1996 (on Disk010) and 1997 (on Disk003) (Box 1)
    - Effigy, Effigy.poe, 1996, and Eff.11, 1997, on Disk003 (Box 1)
    - Effigy 11, Effigy11.poe, 1996, on Disk003 (Box 1)
    - Equinox, Equinox.poe, 1995, on Disk008 (Box 1)
    - February, Feb.poe, 1997, on Disk003 (Box 1)